
//* CHAPTER 0 *//

'<<' is LEFT-associative : if more than one occurence within an expression, each << will use as much of the expression as it can
for its LEFT operand, and as little as it can for its right.
Operators behave according to their operands.

ex) std::cout << "Hello, world!" << std::endl;
  1st << has 'std::cout' as left, '"Helloworld"' as right
  2nd << has 'std::cout<<"Helloworld"' as left, 'std::endl' as right:
  (std::cout << "Hello world!") << std::endl
  1st left = std::cout == std::ostream, right = "helloworld" == string literal => writes right onto left ; results in LEFT OPERAND!
  2nd now has left==std::cout (std::ostream), right = std::endl (MANIPULATOR) ; returns the given STREAM
  ==> RETURN == std::cout
  ';' = "discard return value"

'<<' returns leftside when leftside is ostream and rightside is str literal.
Manipulator manipulates the stream other than writing char.
'<<' returns the stream when leftside is stream and rightside is stream manipulator.
'::' = scope operator -> 'qualified name'


//* CHAPTER 1 *//* STRINGS *//

A variable is an object that has a name, an object is a part of the computer's memory that has a type. The type includes an interface with
the operations that are valid for that type.
STRINGs are always initialized - empty/null string if nothing is given.

Streams buffer output - flushing when: buffer full, when asked to read input, or explicitly, e.g using std::endl;

* We can give a var a value when defining it:  std::string greeting = "Hello, " + name + "!"; --> string literal is CONVERTED to string type
* '+' concatenates string+literal, string+string. (NOT literal+literal)
  OPERATOR takes meaning depending on operands --> OVERLOADING
  
CONST is often used for readability.  It MUST be INITIALIZED at definition time since it will not change later!
This initial value does not need to be const ; can use var as part of initialization (const string val = "Hello, " + name;)

Operators' associativety never changes.  ex) std::cout << s << t == (std::cout << s) << t
'+' is LEFT-associative: ex) "H, " +name +"!" == ("H, "+name) + "!"

var v = value :: This is the value we want v to have
var v2(value) :: CONSTRUCT the var from this value expression (depending on var type)
 ex) const std::string spaces(greeting.size(), ' '); // member function size() + char literal

wchar_t == wide enough
std::string s;
std::string t = s; // copy s - which can be string or string literal
std::string z(n, c);
os << s; // returns os
is >> s; // overwrites previous values ; returns is
s + t;
s.size();

std::string hello = "Hello"; // define var w explicit initial value
std::string stars(100, '*'); // construct var according to type and given expressions
std::string name;            // define var w implicit initialization, which depends on its type


//* CHAPTER 2 *//* LOOPING and COUNTING *//

while (condition) statement;
  where STATEMENT is statement or block
  STATEMENT ends with ';'
  - condition anywhere a 'truth value' is needed

STD::STRING::SIZE_TYPE == the TYPE NAME of number of chars in that string (unsigned)
--> prefer over int!!! (possibly too small...)

RELATIONAL operators have lower precedence than ARITHMETIC operators:  (override with parantheses)
c==cols-1 : cols-1 is calculated first
'||' has lower precedence than RELATIONAL (==) and is LEFT-ASSOCIATIVE ; SHORT-CIRCUIT evaluation ; stops as soon as it knows
'&&' is LEFT-associative, short-circuiting

USING STD::COUT; ==> cout == std::cout; // "using-declaration" -- scopes like elsewhere, e.g. between { }

int r=0;
while (r != rows) {
   ++r;
}
FOR (int r=0; r!=rows; ++r) {} // [0,rows) 'rows' == off-the-end value

FOR (init-statement condition; expression)
   statement
   // 'init statement' == definition, or expression statement
{
   init-statement
   while (condition) {
      statement
	  expression; // expression+';' == statement
   }
}

ASYMMETRIC ranges makes counting easier:
[0,rows) -> rows-0 is the count
[1,rows] -> rows-1 +1 is the count
Also makes invariant easier: "we have written 0 rows so far"

OPERATORS and PRECEDENCE and ASSOCIATIVITY
Most operators are LEFT-associative except ASSIGNMENT, CONDITIONAL, SINGLE-argument operators

HIGH-TO-LOW precedence (grouped):
=======
x.y - member y of x
x[y] - element at index y of x
x++ - increment x, return ORIGINAL value of x
x-- - decrement x, return ORIGINAL value of x
=======
++x - increment, return INCREMENTED value
--x - decrement, return decremented
!x - logical negation
=======
x*y
x/y - if both are integral, so is the result.  The implementation chooses whether to round toward 0 or -<uendelig>
x%y - remainder ; x - ((x/y) *y) ; both must be integral
=======
x+y
x-y
=======
x >> y - ints; x shifted right by y bits. y>0. IF x is ISTREAM, reads from x into y
x << y - ints; x shifted left by y bits. y>0. If x is OSTREAM, write y onto x
=======
x <relop> y - '<' '>' '<=' '>=' - bool
=======
x==y - bool
x!=y
=======
x&&y - bool; are both true? short-circuiting (left-to-right)
=======
x||y - bool; are one of them true? short-circuiting (left-to-right)
=======
x=y - assign; result is x
x <op>= y - compound assign
x ? y:z - evaluates EITHER y or z
=======

size_t = unsigned integral <cstddef> that can hold any object's size
string::size_type = unsigned integral that can hold the size of any string

STATEMENTS:
USING namespace-name::name;  - define 'name' as synonym for 'namespace::name'
type-name name;
type-name name = value;  - define 'name' with type 'type-name' initialized as a COPY of 'value'
type-name name(args);  - define 'name' CONSTRUCTED as appropriate for the given 'args'
expression;  - execute
{ statement(s) }  - block; scope delimitor
while (condition) statement
for (init-statement condition; expression) statement
if (condition) statement
if (condition) statement else statement2
return val;


/////////////////
//* CHAPTER 3 *//
End-of-file on command line: \n ctr-z(win) ctr-d(Unix)
String literals, separated by whitespace only, are automatically concatenated.
Default-initialization - not happening for local vars of built-in type!!

while (cin >> x) {...} - reading a value into x is a side effect of testing this condition - may fail if:
 - end of input
 - input is incompatible with the type of the var
 - hw failure on the input device
 This stream is now unusable until it is RESET!

Needs:
 - store an unknown noof values
 - sort the values afterwards
 - access the middle value(s)
 --> 'vector'

VECTOR is a container; a TEMPLATE CLASS.
Vectors can be INDEXed

Performance requirements are posed on e.g. 'vectors':
- appending a large noof elements can be no worse that proportional to the noof elements
- SORT can be no slower on average than Nlog(N) where N is noof ele

Local vars are DEFAULT-INITIALIZED if not explicitly init'ed.  For built-in types that means UNDEFINED.

VECTOR
vector<T>::size_type
v.begin()
v.end() - one past last
vector<T> v
v.push_back(e)
v[i]
v.size() - noof ele

sort(b, e) - sorts [b,e) non-decreasing - <algorithm>
max(e1, e2) - <algorithm> - must be exactely same type
while (cin>>x)
s.precision(n) - sets precision of stream 's' to 'n' for future output (leaves untouched if no 'n'); returns previous precision
setprecision(n) - returns a value that, when written to stream 's' == s.precision(n) - <iomanip>
streamsize - the type of value expected by setprecision() and returned by precision() - <ios>

Use an object's ::SIZE_TYPE to be implementation independent.  Can be typedef'ed / synonymed to a simpler name


FUNCTIONS
Sending arguments to a functions, parameters are initialized to _copies_ of these values -> CALL BY VALUE
Call by value when the function will change the value of the parameter (e.g. sorting) and it should NOT be sent back

Throwing an exception passes ctr to the error handling part of the program, along with an 'exception object' containing some info.
DOMAIN_ERROR <stdexcept> : a function's args are outside of the accepted value range - string description

vector<double> homework;
vector<double>& hw = homework; // REFERENCE == SYNONYM
vector<double>& hw1 = hw; // hw1 == hw == homework
const vector<double>& chw = hw; // r-o name for hw==homework;

vector<double>& hw2 = chw; // ERROR : chw is const

Parameter= const vector<double>& vd; // direct access w/o copying content ; will not change content ; can be called w const or non-const args

To return more than one value from a func: provide a REFERENCE param in which to put the result == common for user-input funcs
A non-const REF ARG signals the intent to modify the content --- must be called w LVALUE arg; a NON_TEMPORARY obj
Returning stream reference makes it testable

non-const reference arguments must be LVALUE==non-temporary
call by value, or const ref: can be called w any kind of value:
vector<double> emptyvec() {
   vector<double> v;
   return v;
}
grade(midterm, final, emptyvec()); // immediate return: empty 3rd arg
read_hw(cin, emptyvec()); // ERROR: emptyvec() is not an lvalue ; both values are non-const ref

TRY-CATCH
Remember that execution stops
E.g. '<<' executes operations left-to-right, but evaluation of the operands can be done in any order
Avoid more than one side-effect per statement (throw is side effect), especially when input/output is involved